A. E. Housman Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
A. E. Housman Papers 1906-1940
MSS26567
Housman, A. E. (Alfred Edward), 1859-1936
30 items
9 containers
1.8 linear feet
2 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Poet. Chiefly notebooks containing drafts, fair copies, and fragments of Housman's poetry, in addition to a few letters and miscellaneous items. Also includes an analysis of some of the poems by John W. Carter.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Carter, John, 1905-1975.; Housman, A. E. (Alfred Edward), 1859-1936.; Housman, A. E. (Alfred Edward), 1859-1936. Last Poems. 1922.; Housman, A. E. (Alfred Edward), 1859-1936. More Poems. 1936.; Housman, A. E. (Alfred Edward), 1859-1936. Shropshire Lad. 1896.
Subjects
English literature.; English poetry.; Literature.; Poetry.
Titles
Alfred Edward Housman papers
Occupations
Poets.
Provenance
The papers of A. E. Housman, poet, were given to the Library of Congress by Gertrude Clarke Whittal in 1940. Purchases and gifts were added 1942-1969.
Transfers
Photographs and drawings have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Divisio where they are identified as part of the A. E. Housman Papers.
Other Repositories
A collection of Housman correspondence and writings is also at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Ind.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of A. E. Housman are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on two reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1859, Mar. 26 Born, Worcestershire, England
1870 1877 Attended Bromsgrove School, Worcestershire, England
1877 1881 Attended St. John’s College, Oxford, England
1882 1892 Higher division clerk, Patent Office, London, England
1892 Professor of Latin, University College, London, England
1896 Published A Shropshire Lad. London: K. Paul, Trench, Trubner
1911 Kennedy professor of Latin, Cambridge University, Cambridge, England
1922 Published Last Poems. London: G. Richards
1936 Published More Poems. London: J. Cape
1936, Apr. 30 Died, Cambridge, England
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Alfred Edward Housman (1859-1936) span the years 1906-1940 and consist largely of drafts of poems, containing numerous corrections and alterations, most of which appeared in A Shropshire Lad (1896), Last Poems (1922), and More Poems (1936). The bulk of the collection is contained in seven volumes or notebooks and consists of rough drafts, later drafts, fair copies, and fragments of the poet’s writings. An introductory volume contains a foreword and indexes to the other notebooks.
An addition to the collection contains photocopies of the published works noted above. The originals of the published volumes, part of a Housman collection at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana, were annotated by John W. Carter in 1939 with readings from the original manuscripts as transcribed from the notebooks. A considerable number of these readings are no longer visible in the manuscripts themselves, and as such, the photocopies represent an important supplement to the notebooks.
Also in the addition is a photocopy of an analysis of the poems in the notebooks, prepared by Carter and accompanied by a photocopy of an index to the original arrangement of the notebooks. Other material in the addition includes a small number of correspondence and miscellaneous items.
Arrangement of the Papers
The notebooks are arranged in the sequence they were received, and the addition is organized according to type of material.
Container List
*Available on microfilm. Shelf nos. 13,092 and 13,224 (duplicate)
**Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 10,036
- Notebooks, 1906-1939 (Box 1, Reel 1*)
  - Vol.1, foreword and indexes (Box 1, Reel 1*)
  - Vol. 2, notebook A (Box 2, Reel 1*)
  - Vol. 3, notebook B (Box 3, Reel 1*)
  - Vol. 4, notebook C (Box 4, Reel 1*)
  - Vol. 5, notebook D (Box 5, Reel 1*)
  - Vol. 6, notebook E (Box 6, Reel 1*)
  - Vol. 7, notebook F (Box 7, Reel 1*)
  - Vol. 8, unlettered notebook (Box 8, Reel 1*)
- Addition (Box 9, Reel 1**)
  - Correspondence, 1909, 1922, 1929, undated (Box 9)
  - Fragments (Box 9, Reel 1**)
  - Index (Box 9, Reel 1**)
  - Miscellany, 1936-1940, undated (Box 9, Reel 1**)
  - Poems, photocopies of published vols. (Box 9, Reel 1**)
    - A Shropshire Lad (London: E. Grant Richards, 1906. 96pp.) (Box 9, Reel 1**)
    - Last Poems (London: G. Richards, 1922. 78 pp.) (Box 9, Reel 1**)
    - More Poems (London: J. Cape, 1936. 71 pp.) (Box 9, Reel 1**)